<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life skills | Manspeaker - online home of Cliff Manspeaker]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmanspeaker.github.io/categories/life-skills/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmanspeaker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-26T21:24:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmanspeaker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cliff Manspeaker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Acknowledgement]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmanspeaker.github.io/2014/10/26/acknowledgement/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T20:38:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmanspeaker.github.io/2014/10/26/acknowledgement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve found over the years a typical behaviour that has recently been weighing me down when meeting and estimating out projects for potential new clients.</p>

<p>A company representative reaches out to me to introduce a project and discuss their needs either over the phone or set up a meeting to go over it in person. I spend the time reviewing the project outline, technical specifications, etc. to generate an estimate of what I believe is involved with the information given. I&rsquo;ll review when they can expect to receive the proposal of work and send it via email for their review.</p>

<p>That is when it goes south. There are times when I literally hear nothing back. I never expect an immediate response but after a week of nothing, I&rsquo;ll send a follow up email or place a call to get an idea of where they are with their decision. There have been occasions where that still leads to no response which then gets my mind running on where I fell short.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m baffled with all of this technology available to us today to communicate and I can&rsquo;t even get a simple acknowledgement. I really don&rsquo;t have an issue hearing the word &lsquo;No&rsquo; or telling me I&rsquo;m an asshole or I&rsquo;m crazy to think that their project would cost that much.</p>

<p>Any additional feedback would be great as to why I wasn&rsquo;t selected but honestly I&rsquo;d love to just hear that it was received. It is all bonus points if there is a thank you for putting this together, we&rsquo;ve found someone else, or we aren&rsquo;t ready to make a decision, etc.</p>

<p>Maybe the issue is how I present the estimate to clients. I&rsquo;ve been thinking maybe it involves setting up a meeting to review the proposal in person. It then presents the opportunity to ensure all of the main functions are covered along with being able to answer any questions as it&rsquo;s presented. I&rsquo;m not sure if budget and the size of the project come into play as to whether meeting would be too much for what is involved.</p>

<p>As I write this, I&rsquo;m reflecting on how I&rsquo;ve dealt with other companies where I&rsquo;ve needed estimates to put things into perspective. I was recently looking into have our roof reshingled and reached out to four different roofing companies for estimates. Three of those four companies actually came out to measure our roof and take down some information on our home. Within about a week I had been emailed all of the estimates breaking down their costs and time involved. After reviewing each, I emailed the ones we didn&rsquo;t select to simply thank them for their time and let them know we had selected another company to take on our project. It literally took a few minutes and I&rsquo;m sure they appreciated the acknowledgment. One company actually replied to say thank you for the response and offered any help if we ever had any future roof work.</p>

<p>The next time you are looking to get an estimate from a company, think about giving them a quick response to let them know it was received. Is it a necessity? No, but I think it is just a common courtesy to acknowledge that they took the time to present this information for you to make a decision.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's about time]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmanspeaker.github.io/2014/08/18/its-about-time/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-18T08:43:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmanspeaker.github.io/2014/08/18/its-about-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After months, no years, I&rsquo;m finally launching a blog. Based on what you are seeing now, this looks like it shouldn&rsquo;t have taken that long. The problem was that I got in the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Paralysis by analysis</h3>

<p>When I first started developing for the web, I thought it would be a good practice to set up a page for myself to keep an idea of thoughts, help explain the processes I used during my development, etc. Things always kept getting in the way, at least in my mind.</p>

<p>I would debate about which platform I would build my blog on. Should I use Wordpress, Tumblr, just stick to Twitter or make my own custom build? That was about a month of debate and then it got put on the back burner. You start getting busy with client work and you eventually stop thinking about it. Work would start to slow down a bit and I&rsquo;d tell myself that I really need to get back to working on a blog.</p>

<h4>The neverending question loop</h4>

<p>These are the questions that would constantly come back everytime I would get started</p>

<ul>
<li>What layout and colors would work best?</li>
<li>What am I going to write about?</li>
<li>What if no one reads it?</li>
<li>What can I really bring to the table?</li>
<li>Why am I doing this anyway?</li>
</ul>


<p>I finally decided to get back to making this priority at the beginning of the year. A big inspiration to me was reading the book,  <a href="http://executebook.com/" title="The Execute Book">Execute</a>, which had the mantra of just create, not just keep thinking about it. It came down to throwing the questions out of the window and just building. This was a tough process for me as I kept going back to my old ways of thinking. It really comes down to executing something.</p>

<p>When I look at what I have now for my blog, I keep telling myself it&rsquo;s not final. Maybe I&rsquo;ll tweak things here and there, possibly add some features, etc. But the main point is that it&rsquo;s live and it&rsquo;s out there. Now I can start tracking traffic and make adjustments where needed or how I see fit.</p>

<p>Next steps will be to get a schedule for posting that is realistic and take it one day at a time. Thank you for your patience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
